Hi everybody, so my name is Justin Smith I'm an assistant professor of computer science
at Lafayette College and I'm so excited so be here talking to you about my research in
which I explore how automated tools can help us communicate better fixes, and more importantly,
better strategies for fixing the bugs that they detect. So the thing that we strive for -
to strive to do as software to developers is to rise up to a higher level of abstraction.
For example, we don't think anymore about moving electrons through circuits in order to just add
two numbers together. Instead we want to focus on the more important and more interesting higher
level problems like building bots that use hidden Markov models to automatically generate startups.
But the problem is, many of our tools that detect defects in our software systems are stuck in the
Dark Ages. We have tons and tons of tools that are really good at finding problems. We have security
tools, we have linters, we have compilers, we have API misuse detectors, we have static analysis
tools... But these tools don't do a very good job of helping us think at a high level about how to
solve the problems that they detect. To illustrate this problem, let's look at an example. So this is a
common variety of error that students in intro to programming courses might might encounter. So
here the novice programmer is trying to store a value of 1.5 in an integer variable called thing.
And this might seem a really simple error to you, but imagine this programmer is new
to type systems, or new to programming, or perhaps they're new to processing.
So the defect detection tool that we're looking at here is the compiler, which is finding a syntax
error, and it's throwing up a big red flag and saying, you cannot convert from float to int.
So this novice programmer, they don't know what to do, so they do what all of us do, they
type this error message into Google, they click on the first result which is Stack Overflow, and they
see that someone else has had another instance of a very similar problem. So that's good. They go and
check the accepted answer for that problem, and the answer says that they need to change the return
type to float in order to return decimal values. Okay so they change the return type of their setup
method to float and now they're in an even bigger mess than they were when they started. Okay, so what
went wrong? First, there was no explanation: the defect detection tool told the developer "big red
flag, there's a problem" but it didn't explain how they should go about fixing that problem.
Second, there was a bit of a mismatch between the example we saw on Stack Overflow and this
developer's particular instance of the problem. So on Stack Overflow we used variable names like
mutate, and new x, and x, and in this example we use variable names like thing and a method name
called setup. So the developer has to do this cognitively difficult task of finding a match
between these two similar but different concepts. And finally, most importantly, we had different root
causes. So the root cause of the defect here is that there is a mismatch in the assignment types - the
variable assignment - and the mismatch in the Stack Overflow example was a wrong return type.
So I know you all have bigger, bigger problems, right, you're not worrying about converting floats
to ints, but I would argue that your problems are kind of the same. When you get an error that
doesn't make sense, you have to work out all of the low level steps in order to fix that error.
So what we need is to turn our error messages into something that, one, helps you solve the particular
instance of a problem that you're facing at any given point in time, and, two, teaches you a more
effective strategy for fixing problems like that in the future. So that's what we need, and
that's what we did. We built a tool that does just this. So what it does - our tool is called
MatchingRef - it analyzes your code and it analyzes the particular instance of an error message
that you've encountered and it, first, helps you to identify the root cause of the problem that
is generating - that is causing that error to occur. And then it suggests an expert strategy
for fixing those types of defects. So this is what MatchingRef would generate for the example that
we've been looking at so far, and so now we're at that next level of abstraction up. Instead of
worrying about the low level details of how we'd fix an individual problem, we can think about the
higher level strategies that we would choose to fix problems like it. Okay, and this tool and
our approach is not just for type mismatch errors. So this is a mock-up of what MatchingRef
or the - or this idea would look like for a more complex set of errors, for example, finding
path traversal vulnerabilities and security - security vulnerabilities like a path traversal
vulnerability, and sharing an effective strategy for fixing that vulnerability. Okay, so here are a
few places you can go if you want to check out the tool. I hope that you'll try it out, if not only to
just satisfy your curiosity, but it also in hopes that it inspires you to think about the tools that
you create and the tools that you use and how you can help developers think more strategically and
more abstractly about solving the problems that they - that they detect. Thank you.